<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brefe and pleasaunte worke, and sience, of the phelosopher, Pictagoras wherin is declared the aunswer of questyo[n]s which therein be obtained after ye order of thys syence, both for syckens, [and] helth, with dyuers other pretye questions, verye pleasent to pase the tyme whith, taken and getherd out of ye sayd Pictagoras. worke.</title>
            <author>Pythagoras.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1560</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10245</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20524</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101539</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837348</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837348</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1666</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10245)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1666)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1001:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brefe and pleasaunte worke, and sience, of the phelosopher, Pictagoras wherin is declared the aunswer of questyo[n]s which therein be obtained after ye order of thys syence, both for syckens, [and] helth, with dyuers other pretye questions, verye pleasent to pase the tyme whith, taken and getherd out of ye sayd Pictagoras. worke.</title>
                  <author>Pythagoras.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In the Ventre vpon the. iii. Craned wharfe. by me Wyllyam Copland,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprented at Londo[n] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1560?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures:  A B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1666:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:1666:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
A Brefe and pleſaunte Worke, and Sience, of the Pheloſopher, <hi>Pictagoras.</hi> wher in is declared the Aunſwer of Queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which there in be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> order of thys ſyence, both for ſyckens, &amp; helth, with dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other pretye queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, verye pleaſent to paſe the tyme whith, Taken and getherd out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd <hi>Pictagoras.</hi> worke.</p>
            <p>¶ Imprented at Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Ventre vpon the .iii. Traned wharfe. by me Wyllyam Copland.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:1666:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1666:2"/>
            <head>The preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho ſo intendes to know the ſcience of Pitagorie, Fyrſt vnderſtande there is .xxxvi. queſtions wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the beginning. And if queſtion be moued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee for anye of them, or lyke to them, Then it be howes you to wright .xii. Numbers thus .i. ii. iii. iiii. v. vi. vii. viii. ix. x. xi. xii. And dydde hym y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moued the queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to take on of them which that he wyl, Or elſe wri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e xii. numbers and kut them eche frome other. and put them in to a cloſe thinge and let them take one of them by adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Then loke among al your queſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons for that ſame queſtion y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he aſked for. And loke then at the line ende amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges all the .xxxvi. Iudges, as Soull, Ioua, Chore, Eluſon, Swyllam, Tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter. &amp;c. And to euery Iudge longes. xii queſtions, and at the lyne end you ſhal fynd the Iudges name marke wel that Then muſt you count from that Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, er frome the queſtion, tel you come at the number that was choſen, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng that ſame Iudge for one. And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loke at the lyne end and that is the Iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge, kepe wel his name. And then turne to the aunſwers and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, Then counte fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fyrſt aunſwer
<pb facs="tcp:1666:3"/>
of the ſame Iudge tel thou come to the fyrſt number y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was choſen. And when you are at the number, the ſame lyne folowing is the au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwer to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quiſtion. But and the queſtion be in the laſt end of all the queſtions, as in Aquario. or in Piſſibus, and then the numbre that is choſen be more then there be queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons after wryte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as yf the number that was choſen be .x. or moo, and there be on queſtion, or on beneth writen then muſte you begene at the queſtion and count that for on, and ſo tel forth to the end, as Ores, that is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt of Piſſibus And then begene aboue agayne, as at Soull, the firſt of Arietes, to you come at the ful number that was choſen and that ſame Index is the Iudge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, marke his name and turne to yt amonge the aunſwers, and tell to you come to the nomber choſen. and that ſame lyne is the aunſwer to the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="questions">
            <pb facs="tcp:1666:3"/>
            <head>¶ Here folowes after the queſtions to eche in his degre, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaye the fyrſte iii. queſtions longes to Aries, the next iii. queſtions longes to Taurus, and ſo to all the xii. Sygnes and at the laſt end be the Iudges written w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber where you ſhall fynde then amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges the aunſwers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>F y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yong child ſhal lyue &amp; be hapy. in. primo. gradus. Ariete</p>
            <p>If ther ſhalbe winning. in .ii. gradus. Arietes</p>
            <p>If the waye ſhalbe eaſye. in .iii. gradus. Arietes</p>
            <p>If the yere ſhalbe plentious. in. primo gradus. Taurus</p>
            <p>If he ſhall haue chyldren. in .ii. gradus. Taurus</p>
            <p>If the ſycke ſhall eſkape. in .iii. gradus. Taurus</p>
            <p>If he ſhall wed awyfe. in. primo. gradus. Gemine</p>
            <p>If he ſhall eſkape his drede. in .ii. gradus. Gemine</p>
            <p>If he ſhall fulfyll hys waye. in .iii. gradus. Gemine</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1666:4"/>
If he ſhal haue grace with kynges. in primo gradus Cauncer</p>
            <p>If he ſhall haue prophet of his lowe. in ſecundus gradus. Cauncer</p>
            <p>If he ſhall ouer come his enemyes. in tartio gradus. Cauncer</p>
            <p>If the Youth ſhalbe beter then the age in primo gradus. Leonis</p>
            <p>If he ſhall pay his Dette. in .ii. gradus. Leonis</p>
            <p>If the Meſenger ſhall come agayne. in .iii. gradus. Leonis</p>
            <p>What ende ſhalbe of the thyng begon. in primo gradus. Vergo</p>
            <p>What child y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> woman ſhal bring forth in .ii. gradus. Vergo</p>
            <p>If the ſeruaunt ſent ſhall come agayn. in .iii. gradus. Vergo</p>
            <p>If thy felowſhype ſhall be good. in primo gradus. Libra</p>
            <p>If he ſhall haue Heritage. in .ii. gradus. Libra</p>
            <p>If he ſhall wene. in .iii. gradus Libra</p>
            <p>If he ſhall haue eaſe in his labour. in primo. gradus. Scorpio</p>
            <p>If he ſhal haue his wyll. in .ii. gradus. Scorpio</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1666:4"/>
If the man that is take ſhall aſkpe. in .iii. gradus. Scorpio</p>
            <p>If he ſhalbe hole or naye, in .primo. gradus. Sagittario</p>
            <p>If the Pore ſhalbe ryche in .ii. gradus. Sagittario</p>
            <p>If chaungyng of place be good. in .iii. gradus. Sagittario</p>
            <p>If the thyng bought ſhalbe eſye. in .primo. gradus. Capricorin</p>
            <p>If the tydynges be trewe. in .ii. gradus. Capricorni</p>
            <p>If he that is gone ſhal come agayne. in .iii. gradus. Capricorni</p>
            <p>If he ſhall get in pleatyng. in, primo. gradus. Aquario.</p>
            <p>If he that thou aſketh for lyue or no. in .ii. gradus. Aqua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>io</p>
            <p>If thy dreame be good or no. in .iii. gradus. Aquario</p>
            <p>If be trieng in batell or no. in primo. gradus, Piſſibus</p>
            <p>What of frindſhype is to thee. in .ii. gradus. Piſſibus</p>
            <p>If the thyng loſt ſhalbe recouerer. in .iii. gradus. Piſſibus</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="questions">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1666:5"/>
GRadus. Arietes. Nemeruth to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram. to Soull. .i.</p>
            <p>gradus. Arietes. Embrafell to Gelty. to Ionas. .ii</p>
            <p>gradus. Arietes. Ariok. to Emechi. to Chore. iii.</p>
            <p>Gradus. Taurus. Decaldel iomech. Aura. to Cluſon. iiii.</p>
            <p>gradus. Taurus. Kirall. to Chaaph. to Cuilam. v.</p>
            <p>gradus, Taurus. Bilaak. to Cho. to Choter. vi.</p>
            <p>Gradus. Gemine. Fraye. to Vney. to Ternagon. vii</p>
            <p>gradus. Gemine. Belſarae, to Heden. to Mery. viii</p>
            <p>gradus. Gemine. Haris, to Felcu. to Thura. ix</p>
            <p>Gradus. Cauncer. Abiad. to Meleche. to Thoab. x</p>
            <p>gradus. Cauncer. Achar. to Yamall. to Salap. xi.</p>
            <p>gradus. Cauncer. Guiſam. to Os. to Arben. xii</p>
            <p>Gradus. Liones. Quiſe. to Quelas. to Aia. xiii</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1666:5"/>
gradus. Liones. Yram, to Hethind. to Efra. xiiii.</p>
            <p>gradus. Leonis. Ahohar, to Namar. to Sechoth. xv.</p>
            <p>Gradus Virgines. Harue, to Beth. to Gaap. xvi.</p>
            <p>gradus. Virgines. Helen, to Giell. to Iana. xvii</p>
            <p>gradus. virgines. Chera, to keph. to Thalet. xviii.</p>
            <p>Gradus. Libra. Aſaell, to Yall. to Iouis. xix</p>
            <p>gradus. Libra. Naab, to Zelam. to Zalem. xx</p>
            <p>gradus. Libra. Agar, to Riab. to Edir. xxi</p>
            <p>Gradus. Aas. to Gehei. to Zira. xxii</p>
            <p>gradus. Scor, to Thoi. to Dure to Hes. xxiii</p>
            <p>gradus. Scor. Oyf, to Olmeth. to Camni. xxiiii</p>
            <p>Gradus Sagita. Salam, to Zirat to Rioth. xxv</p>
            <p>gradus, Sagita. Amath. to Zep. to Azoth. xxvi</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1666:6"/>
Gradus, Sagita, Thoell. to Aphen to Zaph. xxvii</p>
            <p>Gradus. Capricor. Aka. to Lamui. to Taph. xxviii</p>
            <p>gradus. Capricor. Alker, to Zok. to Baell. xxix</p>
            <p>gradus. Capricor. Laake. to Adud. to Salath. xxx</p>
            <p>Gradus. Aquarius. Yſake. to Napill. too Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n. xxxi</p>
            <p>gradus. Aquari. Salmay. to Du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lday to Syray. xxxii</p>
            <p>gradus. Aquari. Cablye. to Elcha. to Sebail. xxxiii</p>
            <p>Gradus. Piſſis. Sinatherib. to Oky. to Aſtaroth. xxxiiii</p>
            <p>gradus. Piſſis. Vida. to Amen. to Euan. xxxv</p>
            <p>gradus. Piſſis. Widgad, to Cuban. to Ores. xxxvi</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="judgments">
            <pb facs="tcp:1666:6"/>
            <head>¶ Here after foloweth the Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts and at each end of them a number. And after euerye Iudge ſhall you fynde the aunſwer that you ſeke after. And they be .xii. in number to euerie Iudge, and ar aunſwered in on lyne.</head>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Index. Soull.</head>
               <p>i. THe yonge chylde ſhall l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue and get children with out trauell.</p>
               <p>ii. The theft, or the thinge loſſe ſhalbe recouered.</p>
               <p>iii. All thy frendes be wel with thee.</p>
               <p>iiii. By tryeng and battell, ſhall turne into peace.</p>
               <p>v. Thy Dreame is after thy deſyre good.</p>
               <p>vi. He lyueth, and ſhall come ſone.</p>
               <p>vii. Thou ſhalt get the ple, for thou aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the truth.</p>
               <p>viii. He that is gone ſhall come againe</p>
               <p>ix. The tydinges be good and trewe.</p>
               <p>x. Thou ſhalt longe haue thyn Erita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge.</p>
               <p>xi. Beware of chaungrnge of place.</p>
               <p>xii. Yf thou be pore thou ſhalt be riche.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Ioua .ii.</head>
               <p>i. ALl thy wynninge ſhalbe with trauayle and ſone loſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1666:7"/>
ii. He ſhalbe hole, but nat lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g lufe after</p>
               <p>iii. Theft &amp; thing loſt ſhalbe recuered</p>
               <p>iiii. Thy felowes loueth the nat but bake bytes thee.</p>
               <p>v. Be tryeng and batell ſhalbe turned to peace.</p>
               <p>vi. Thy dreame is prophetable to thy frendes and thou ſhalt wel hape.</p>
               <p>vii. He is ſeeke &amp; hardelye ſhal alkape.</p>
               <p>viii. You ſhalbe the beter for the Law.</p>
               <p>ix. He that is gone, ſhall come againe</p>
               <p>x. Tydynges ſhalbe chaunged.</p>
               <p>xi. Thou ſhalt haue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou coueteſſe of eryrage loſte.</p>
               <p>xii. It is not prophetable to chaunge thy place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Chore .iii.</head>
               <p>i. THou ſhalt fulfyl that thou wylt in thy waye.</p>
               <p>ii. Thou ſhalt prophet in Marchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes.</p>
               <p>iii. The chylde ſhal lyue and his daies ſhalbe mayney.</p>
               <p>iiii. Theft nor thyng loſte, ſhall not be recouered.</p>
               <p>v. Thy frendes loueth thee well, and be glad to playſe thee.</p>
               <p>vi. Be trieng &amp; debat ſhalbe nere y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end</p>
               <p>vii. Thy dreame ſhalbe good.</p>
               <p>viii He that is gone is hole.</p>
               <p>ix. He ſhall ouer come in his cauſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1666:7"/>
x. He that is gone, ſhall not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e again</p>
               <p>xi. Tydynges be trewe.</p>
               <p>xii. Eretage ſhall increſe in thy hand.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Cluſon.</head>
               <p>i. THe frutes of the yere ſhulde be many.</p>
               <p>ii. It is a longe way &amp; of good end.</p>
               <p>iii. Thy wynnyng ſhalbe goode.</p>
               <p>iiii. The yonge chylde ſhall lyue.</p>
               <p>v. Theft nor thing loſt, ſhal not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered.</p>
               <p>vi. Thy frendes loueth the but no thar telye.</p>
               <p>vii. Be trieng and batell ſhuld incres.</p>
               <p>viii. Thy dreme is to be douted.</p>
               <p>ix. He is dede or almoſt dede.</p>
               <p>x. In ſtriuyng y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt be ouer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men</p>
               <p>xi. He ſhalbe chekyd, in coming again</p>
               <p>xii. The tydynges be ſouth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Guilam .v.</head>
               <p>i. THou ſhalt haue childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and the moſt part Doughtren.</p>
               <p>ii. And muche Frute ſhalbe this yere</p>
               <p>iii. He ſhall haue prophet in his waye</p>
               <p>iiii. The wining ſhalbe of good &amp; right</p>
               <p>v. The chyld ſhall lyue and prophet.</p>
               <p>vi. Theft &amp; things loſt ſhalbe reſtored</p>
               <p>vii. Thy frendes loueth thee fenedlye.</p>
               <p>viii. Be trieng ſhalbe well endyd.</p>
               <p>ix Thy dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is good, fer fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g.</p>
               <p>x. The man lyueth in good ſtate.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1666:8"/>
xi Thou ſhalt haue thy cauſe at thy wyll.</p>
               <p>xii. He ſhall come agayne that is gone</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Choter .vi.</head>
               <p>i. YT is dought of the ſeke, for he ſhall haue greuaunce.</p>
               <p>ii. He ſhall haue few ſonues and ſyke.</p>
               <p>iii. Frutes ſhall fayle vtterlye.</p>
               <p>iiii. He ſhall not prophet in the waye.</p>
               <p>v. The ſhalbe lytell wyneng.</p>
               <p>vi. The chyldes dayes ſhalbe ſhorte.</p>
               <p>vii. Thing loſt ſhall not be reſtored.</p>
               <p>viii. Thy felowes loueth thee.</p>
               <p>ix. The Debate is heuye to hym that begane it.</p>
               <p>x. Thy Dreame is right heuye.</p>
               <p>xi. The man is hole and ſound.</p>
               <p>xii. Yf thou take the cauſe thou ſhake wyne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Ternagon .vii.</head>
               <p>i, THou ſhalte haue the woman at wyll.</p>
               <p>ii. The ſycke ſhalbe grued &amp; deliuered</p>
               <p>iii. Thy chyldren ſhalbe Maſculen.</p>
               <p>iiii. The laſt frut of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> yere ſhalbe good</p>
               <p>v The lyfe ſhalbe good and longe.</p>
               <p>vi. Thou ſhalt wen muche with ſtren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ght.</p>
               <p>vii. Thy chyldren ſhuld lyue well.</p>
               <p>viii. The thefte ſhalbe made open and found.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1666:8"/>
vi Thou ſhalte ouer come them that be agaynſt thee.</p>
               <p>x. Tournyeng, and batell ſhall end in peace.</p>
               <p>xi. The end of thy dreame ſhalbe good</p>
               <p>xii. He lyueth fer hence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Merye .viii.</head>
               <p>i THou ſhalte heueley aſkape thy diede.</p>
               <p>ii Thou ſhalt not prophet by this wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man.</p>
               <p>iii. The ſycke ſhall dye.</p>
               <p>iiii. Thou ſhalt haue no doughters.</p>
               <p>v. There ſhalbe lytell frutte this yere.</p>
               <p>vi. It is good to go but not ryght pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetable.</p>
               <p>vii. Yt is good to wynne of eritage eld<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rowde.</p>
               <p>viii. The chyld ſhall dye,</p>
               <p>ix. Hope neuer after the thyng loſt.</p>
               <p>x. Thy frend ſhal haue eaſe &amp; prophet</p>
               <p>xi. The batell ſhal not indure, and the begenner ſhall ouer come.</p>
               <p>xii. Beleue not thy Dreame for it is to dred.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Thura .ix.</head>
               <p>i. THe waye ſhalbe paſſed at leki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g.</p>
               <p>ii. Dought not thy dred, but take with the gold for thy nede.</p>
               <p>iii. You ſhall get her with muche tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1666:9"/>
iiii. The Sycke ſhalbe greued and yet ſkape.</p>
               <p>v. Thou ſhalt haue ſonnes, &amp; dough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
               <p>vi. The Frutes ſhalbe right good this yere.</p>
               <p>vii. The waye ſhalbe long, but not pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phitable.</p>
               <p>viii Thou ſhalt wyne of thy harme by marchandyes.</p>
               <p>ix The chyld ſhal lyue long.</p>
               <p>x, It is happe of fyndyng of the thefte and it ſhalbe knowen.</p>
               <p>xi Thy frend ſhall prophet withe thee or to thee in batall.</p>
               <p>xii. The ſtryte ſhalbe ended, and peace ſhalbe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Thoab .x.</head>
               <p>i. THou ſhalt haue eaſe in ſeruiſes of Lordes.</p>
               <p>ii. The waye ſhal not be paſſed.</p>
               <p>iii Thou ſhalt eſkape great dred.</p>
               <p>iiii. You ſhall haue her at thy wyll.</p>
               <p>v. The ſycke ſhall eſkape baſtyley</p>
               <p>vi. You ſhall haue ſonnes.</p>
               <p>vii. The Frutes ſhalbe good that yere</p>
               <p>viii. You ſhall wenne and prophete in the waye.</p>
               <p>ix. Thy wynnyng ſhalbe of thy offece</p>
               <p>x. Thy chyld ſhal prophet &amp; long lyue</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1666:9"/>
xi. The thyng loſt ſhall ſone be goten.</p>
               <p>xii. You ſhall haue prophet withe thye felowes and frendes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Salaph .xi.</head>
               <p>i. IN this lowe you ſhal haue ꝓphet</p>
               <p>ii. The ſeruyſe, ſhalbe eaſye.</p>
               <p>iii. The tyme is good to go.</p>
               <p>iiii. Dred ſhall torne in to good.</p>
               <p>v. Thou ſhalt not prophet with thys woman.</p>
               <p>vi. The ſyke ſhalbe heuye, and eſkape</p>
               <p>vii. You ſhal haue ryche Sonnes.</p>
               <p>viii. The trutes of this yere ſhalb pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetable.</p>
               <p>ix. The waye is heuye.</p>
               <p>x. The theft ſhall come to thee in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, and peace.</p>
               <p>xi. The chyld ſhall lyue and heale.</p>
               <p>xii. Thinges loſt ſhalbe goten after de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpayre.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Arben .xii.</head>
               <p>i. HOpe thee from thy enemye.</p>
               <p>ii. Go from a gylfull enemye.</p>
               <p>iii. Serue no kyng, nor Prence.</p>
               <p>iiii. He ſhall fulfyl his waye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> trauell</p>
               <p>v. Thou ſhalt haue good of thy dred.</p>
               <p>vi. Wed nat this woman.</p>
               <p>vii. The ſycke ſhall eſkape.</p>
               <p>viii. Thy foes ſhall fall vpon thee and agaynſte thee.</p>
               <p>ix. Frut ſhalbe lytell.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1666:10"/>
x. The waye ſhalbe heauy</p>
               <p>xi. Wynning ſhalbe found.</p>
               <p>xii. the chyld ſhall lyue but a whyle.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Aia .xiii.</head>
               <p>i. IN youth you ſhalbe good</p>
               <p>ii. You ſhall haue Lordſhype ouer thyne Enemyes.</p>
               <p>iii. It is good to kepe a frend</p>
               <p>iiii. You ſhal prophetin y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kings grace</p>
               <p>v. On the waye ſhalbe a paſſion &amp; not prophet.</p>
               <p>vi. Dought the not of the dred</p>
               <p>vii. thy Meſage is good.</p>
               <p>viii. the Syke ſhalbe hole and ſound.</p>
               <p>ix thy Fone, ſhall haue powre ouer y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>.</p>
               <p>x. there ſhalbe lytell frute this yere.</p>
               <p>xi. the way ſhalbe eſye.</p>
               <p>xii. You ſhall wyne mouche</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Efera .xiiii.</head>
               <p>i. THy det ſhalbe payd w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> good wil</p>
               <p>ii. He ſhall prophet in the ende of his dayes.</p>
               <p>iii there ſhalbe a end, of enuemite</p>
               <p>iiii. A Lorde ſhalbe his louer</p>
               <p>v Be in ſere of kynges.</p>
               <p>vi. The waye ſhalbe ended w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> trauayl</p>
               <p>vii Care not of that thou dredes</p>
               <p>viii. Wedyng acordeth not for it is loſt</p>
               <p>ix The ſycke ſhalbe hole</p>
               <p>x You ſhall haue no chyldren</p>
               <p>xi Frute of the yere ſhalbe good</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1666:10"/>
xii you ſhal wene &amp; prophet in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Sochoth .xv.</head>
               <p>i. THe meſenger ſhall come ſoune agayne,</p>
               <p>ii the det ſhalbe gotten with hardines</p>
               <p>iii Tho youth ſhalbe better than age.</p>
               <p>iiii Thy father, and Mother ſhalbe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemye to thee</p>
               <p>v you ſhall Ioye of your lowe</p>
               <p>vi you ſhall prophete in the grace of Prynces.</p>
               <p>vii The waye ſhalbe badde</p>
               <p>viii. Feare nat thye dred.</p>
               <p>ix This wedynge ſhall indure but a whyle.</p>
               <p>x the ſycke ſhalbe delyuered.</p>
               <p>xi Thou ſhalt noryſhe chyldren that ſhall hate thee.</p>
               <p>xii The Frute ſhalbe ryppe and not prophetable.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Gaap .xvi.</head>
               <p>i. THe end ſhalbe good.</p>
               <p>ii The meſenger ſhall come well after taryeng.</p>
               <p>iii Det ſhall come to thy prophet</p>
               <p>iiii He ſhall proue well in age</p>
               <p>v He ſhalbe lorde of all his enymes</p>
               <p>vi. Broken frendſhype is not fened</p>
               <p>vii. The kynges ſeruyce is vnfrutfull</p>
               <p>viii. He ſhall fayle in the waye</p>
               <p>ix Dred is to be doughted.</p>
               <p>x yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wed her y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art ouer maſtered.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1666:11"/>
xi. The ſycke ſhall dye.</p>
               <p>xii. He ſhalbe baran vpon earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Iana .xvii.</head>
               <p>i. THe mother ſhalbe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> .ii. childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>ii. The end ſhalbe moyne.</p>
               <p>iii. The Melenger ſhal come w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ioye.</p>
               <p>iiii. Striuing ſhalbe vnbynding.</p>
               <p>v. All his dayes ſhalbe in payes.</p>
               <p>vi. All tyme he ſhal well behaue hym.</p>
               <p>vii. This lowe is faynynglye.</p>
               <p>viii. It is parell to ſerue kynges.</p>
               <p>ix. The waye ſhalbe helfull.</p>
               <p>x. Myſcefe is to buſye folke.</p>
               <p>xi. Yf you wede a wyfe you ſhalbe a-huſbaund.</p>
               <p>xii. The ſycke ſhall eſkape.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Thalet .xviii.</head>
               <p>i. THe ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſhal not go out, but alwaye wylbe bound.</p>
               <p>ii. She ſhalbe greued in baringe of a daughter.</p>
               <p>iii. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end of his daies he ſhalbe pore</p>
               <p>iiii. The meſenger ſhall come agayne.</p>
               <p>v. Thy Det ſhalbe payd.</p>
               <p>vi. The end ſhalbe better then the be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gynning.</p>
               <p>vii. He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> riſeth againſt y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſhal not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</p>
               <p>viii. His lowe is full of vnſtablenes.</p>
               <p>ix. Go fro a Prence, and his workes.</p>
               <p>x. You ſhall do good in the waye.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1666:11"/>
xi. There ſhalbe dred.</p>
               <p>xii. You ſhall not Ioye of that woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ende.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Iouis. xix,</head>
               <p>i. THy felowſhepe is good.</p>
               <p>ii. He ſhalbe oft deliuered w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>y.</p>
               <p>iii. She ſhall haue ſonnes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> be ſayre.</p>
               <p>iiii. In y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> end of his dayes he ſhal haue eays.</p>
               <p>v. The Meſenger ſhall tary in comi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g agayne.</p>
               <p>vi. Det ſhalbe payd with chyding.</p>
               <p>vii. Euyll goyng out, is of euell begin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning.</p>
               <p>viii. He is a enemy &amp; a ſhrow beware.</p>
               <p>ix. The thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g is loued but nat thi ſelfe.</p>
               <p>x. A Prences grace is more preſyous then golde.</p>
               <p>xi. A longe waye, abrdis nat prophet</p>
               <p>xii. Dred ſhall vanyſhe and thou ſhalt well happe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Zalem .xx.</head>
               <p>i. HE ſhal haue eritage in the end with out lawe.</p>
               <p>ii. Felowſhepe ſhall not be feyned.</p>
               <p>iii. The ſeruaunte ſhalbe deliuered w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out monye.</p>
               <p>iiii. She ſhal haue a doughter, &amp; fowle.</p>
               <p>v. Age ſhalbe worthy and good.</p>
               <p>vi. Men away <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>res y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Meſenger to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me him in his home comyng.</p>
               <p>vii. Det ſhalbe paid with ſtrength.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1666:12"/>
ix. Enemyes ſhalbe enuyous</p>
               <p>x In thy lowe ſhalbe no prophet</p>
               <p>xi The Kynges grace is ſleper</p>
               <p>xii the waye ſhalbe layd at thy wyll</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Edir. xxi,</head>
               <p>i THou ſhalt prophet in marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes.</p>
               <p>ii you ſhal go to eritage</p>
               <p>iii. Ther ſhalbe manye deſcatfull in felowſhepe.</p>
               <p>iiii. He that is take, ſhalbe delyuered</p>
               <p>v She ſhal haue ſonnes.</p>
               <p>vi. you ſhalbe prayſed in the ende</p>
               <p>vii the meſenger ſhal come ſone again</p>
               <p>viii. the det ſhalbe paid w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out greuance</p>
               <p>ix. he that is taken ſhal go out.</p>
               <p>x Be tryeng of enmite ſhalbe good, or peace take of thy enemye.</p>
               <p>xi. Get a trew frend.</p>
               <p>xii you ſhall not prophet to a prence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Zira .xxii.</head>
               <p>i. ALl thy workes ſhuld be eſye &amp; gracious.</p>
               <p>ii A voyd no cuſtum in marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ys</p>
               <p>iii. Erytage ſhalbe wenning.</p>
               <p>iiii. the felowſhepe ſhalbe good</p>
               <p>v He that is take ſhal go out by moni</p>
               <p>vi She ſhall haue a child and no ioye ther with.</p>
               <p>vii the old man ſhalbe ſone ryche.</p>
               <p>viii The meſenger ſhall come agayne vn ſped.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1666:12"/>
ix thy dettes ſhalbe gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by ſtrenght</p>
               <p>x A feble beginning ſhal haue a good end.</p>
               <p>xi thyne enemye ſall ouer come thee.</p>
               <p>xi. this frendſhype is nat prophetable</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Hes .xxiii.</head>
               <p>i THou ſhalt not haue thy deſyer.</p>
               <p>ii He ſhall fayle in the myddes of fyght.</p>
               <p>iii Seke wenning &amp; you ſhal haue it</p>
               <p>iiii you ſhall go to erytage.</p>
               <p>v the felowſype is fayned.</p>
               <p>vi He that is take ſhal go out without gyftes.</p>
               <p>vii She ſhal haue ſorow after chyldig</p>
               <p>viii. In the end he ſhalbe made pore.</p>
               <p>ix The meſenger is beſet, but he ſhall eſkape.</p>
               <p>x the det ſhalbe well payde</p>
               <p>xi the ende ſhalbe in a mayne, nether full good ne bade.</p>
               <p>xii Of hate, ſhall peace be made.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Camm .xxiiii.</head>
               <p>i HE y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is take ſhall not go forthe</p>
               <p>ii thou ſhalt not haue thy deſyer</p>
               <p>iii Euell ſhalbe the goynge out of the workes.</p>
               <p>iiii, Lytel gayne ſhalbe in marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dies</p>
               <p>v In ſtrenght y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt haue eritage.</p>
               <p>vi this felowſhipe ſhal get y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> winning</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1666:13"/>
vii. The ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhal not come agayn,</p>
               <p>viii. She with chyld ſhalbe dyſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zed.</p>
               <p>ix. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end of his dayes he ſhalbe pore</p>
               <p>x. The meſenger ſhal not well hap in the waye.</p>
               <p>xi. He ſhall ſhew for det.</p>
               <p>xii. The end ſhalbe good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Rioth .xxv.</head>
               <p>i. HE ſhalbe hole of bodye.</p>
               <p>ii. He that is in pryſen ſhal ſone go out.</p>
               <p>iii. Thou ſhalt fulfyll thy deſyer.</p>
               <p>iiii. In workes y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt haue pore ſprit.</p>
               <p>v. Thy Marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dies ſhalbe ſone ſold</p>
               <p>vi, Thou ſhalt haue thyne Heritage.</p>
               <p>vii. This felowſhype is good.</p>
               <p>viii. Thy ſeruaunt ſhal not go fre.</p>
               <p>ix. She ſhall haue a ſonne.</p>
               <p>x. In the end he ſhall haue his wyll.</p>
               <p>xi. The meſenger ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e anon again</p>
               <p>xii. Thou ſhalt paye thy det at thy wyl</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>A Zoth .xxv.</head>
               <p>i. YOu ſhall helpe the pore wyth thy good.</p>
               <p>ii. He ſhal lyue awhile with trauayl.</p>
               <p>iii. He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is taken ſhalbe longe in hold.</p>
               <p>iiii. Thou ſhalt haue that thou deſireſt</p>
               <p>v. Al that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> labereſt abought ſhal ꝓfer</p>
               <p>vi. You ſhal leſe in Marchandyes.</p>
               <p>vii. You ſhal ſpend muche in heritage.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1666:13"/>
viii. The felowſhype is not good.</p>
               <p>ix. Thy ſeruaunt ſhal not go free.</p>
               <p>x. She ſhal haue a chyld &amp; ioye therof.</p>
               <p>xi. In his end he ſhall haue worſhype.</p>
               <p>xii. The meſenger ſhall tarrye &amp; come agayne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Zaph .xxvii.</head>
               <p>i. CHanginge of place is good.</p>
               <p>ii. Pouerte ſhalbe heuy.</p>
               <p>iii. He ſhal not be longe hole.</p>
               <p>iiii. He that is taken ſhall ſone ſkape.</p>
               <p>v. Thou ſhalt haue thy deſyre.</p>
               <p>vi. The beginning of thy worke ſhal-be prophetable.</p>
               <p>vii. Marchandiſe ſhalbe prophitable.</p>
               <p>viii. You ſhall haue Herytage.</p>
               <p>ix. Seke a trewe felow.</p>
               <p>x. Thy ſeruaunt ſhalbe free.</p>
               <p>xi. She ſhall haue a child &amp; after dye.</p>
               <p>xii. In her end ſhe ſhall Ioye hym.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Taph .xxviii.</head>
               <p>i. THe Land that thou holdeſt ſhalbe fortunate.</p>
               <p>ii. The chaungyng is right good.</p>
               <p>iii. The power ſhalbe ſone at eue.</p>
               <p>iiii. Helth ſhalbe ryght nygh.</p>
               <p>v. He that is take ſhal not be delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſone.</p>
               <p>vi. Thou ſhalt haue thy wyll.</p>
               <p>vii. Thy worke ſhalbe, good and beſte at the ende.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1666:14"/>
viii. Marchandies of beſtes is good.</p>
               <p>ix. thou ſhault not haue erytage</p>
               <p>x Louing feloſhepe ſhalbe ended</p>
               <p>xi the ſeruaunt ſhall not be delyuered</p>
               <p>xii It ſhalbe parel of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chyld</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Bael. xxix,</head>
               <p>i THe tythynges be trew</p>
               <p>ii Erth bought is winning</p>
               <p>iii Chaungyng is horte</p>
               <p>iiii the pore hath good fortune</p>
               <p>v He ſhalbe hole of bodye</p>
               <p>vi He that is take ſhal not be boughte agayne.</p>
               <p>vii He ſhal fayle in the medeſt of hys wyll.</p>
               <p>viii. The worke is nought.</p>
               <p>ix Of marchandyes cometh winyng.</p>
               <p>x you ſhall haue Ioye of Herytage.</p>
               <p>xi. Thy felowſhype ſhalbe accorded.</p>
               <p>xii. The ſeruaunt ſhal go free</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Salach .xxx.</head>
               <p>i HE that is gone ſhal com again</p>
               <p>ii The tydynges ſhalbe chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged</p>
               <p>iii Lond bought ſhal not be ꝓphetable</p>
               <p>iiii The chaungyng is right nought.</p>
               <p>v The pore ſhalbe riche by trauayll</p>
               <p>vi The hole ſhalbe ſycke</p>
               <p>vii He that is taken, ſhalbe delyuered</p>
               <p>viii. you ſhall nat ſe that you deſyer</p>
               <p>ix Pheſycke ſhalbe prophetable</p>
               <p>x Marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſe wyl not be prophetable</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1666:14"/>
xi you ſhal not haue herytage.</p>
               <p>xii Felowſhep is trew.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Naſmon .xxxi.</head>
               <p>i HE ſhall ouer come in his olde age.</p>
               <p>ii He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is gone ſhal not come agayne</p>
               <p>iii The tydinges be trew</p>
               <p>iiii you ſhalbe glad of land bought</p>
               <p>v The chaungyng ſhalbe but meane</p>
               <p>vi. The pore ſhall Ioye</p>
               <p>vii. He ſhalbe hole and ſtrenge.</p>
               <p>viii. He that is take ſhal eſcape</p>
               <p>ix. you ſhall haue no ioye of hym that you aſke for.</p>
               <p>x. The dide of Batell is good</p>
               <p>xi. Marchandyes, is prophetable</p>
               <p>xii. you ſhall haue erytage.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Siray .xxxii.</head>
               <p>i. HE lyueth that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> aſketh after.</p>
               <p>ii He ſhalbe ouer come in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>iii. He that is gone ſhal come agayne.</p>
               <p>iiii. The tydinges ſhuldbe chaunged.</p>
               <p>v. Lond bought ſhall not be frutfull.</p>
               <p>vi. Chaungyng ſhalbe good.</p>
               <p>vii. The pore ſhal haue deſes.</p>
               <p>viii. The hole man ſhall lyue.</p>
               <p>ix. He that is taken ſhall eſkape.</p>
               <p>x. Thou ſhalt do that thou deſyereſt.</p>
               <p>xi. Thy workes ſhalbe fulfellyd.</p>
               <p>xii. You ſhall haue wynning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <pb facs="tcp:1666:15"/>
               <head>Zebai .xxxiii.</head>
               <p>i. THy dream ſhall not be good.</p>
               <p>ii. He is nat hole.</p>
               <p>iii. He ſhal nat haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lawe</p>
               <p>iiii. He that is gone ſhall come againe</p>
               <p>v. The tydinges be trew.</p>
               <p>vi. In a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kyng is prophet.</p>
               <p>vii. Changyng ſhalbe prophytable.</p>
               <p>viii. The pore ſhalbe relyued.</p>
               <p>ix. He is hole that thou aſketh after.</p>
               <p>x. He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is taken ſhall not come again</p>
               <p>xi. Thou ſhalt haue thy wyll.</p>
               <p>xii. Thou ſhalte nat prophet in thy workes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Aſtaroth, xxxiiii.</head>
               <p>i. THe batell ſhalbe long enough.</p>
               <p>ii. Thy dreme ſhalbe trew,</p>
               <p>iii. He that you aſke after is alyue.</p>
               <p>iiii. In the law you ſhalbe ouer come.</p>
               <p>v. He that is gone ſhall not come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne.</p>
               <p>vi. the tydinges be ſtable.</p>
               <p>vii. the Lande that thou haſte bought ſhalbe Barane.</p>
               <p>viii. Changyng hath no good chaunce</p>
               <p>ix. Pouerte ſhalbe heauy.</p>
               <p>x. Helth is nye, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>knes ſhal depart.</p>
               <p>xi. the Priſone ſhalbe broken.</p>
               <p>xii. Wyth trauayll, thou ſhalte haue thy wyll.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <pb facs="tcp:1666:15"/>
               <head>Euan .xxxv.</head>
               <p>i. THy frend loueth thee.</p>
               <p>ii. the tryeng, and battayl ſhalbe peaſed.</p>
               <p>iii. thy Dreme is to dought.</p>
               <p>iiii. He is ſycke that thou aſketh after.</p>
               <p>v. the cauſe ſhalbe ended.</p>
               <p>vi. He that is flede ſhall come agayne</p>
               <p>vii. tydinges be trew.</p>
               <p>viii. the land bought ſhalbe good.</p>
               <p>ix. Changyng is prophetable</p>
               <p>x. the pore ſhall haue remedye.</p>
               <p>xi. the end ſhalbe Ioye.</p>
               <p>xii. He that is take ſhall a ſkape.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="judgment">
               <head>Ores .xxxvi.</head>
               <p>i. THeft ſhall not be reſtored.</p>
               <p>ii. Tryſt nat on thy frendes.</p>
               <p>iii. Wrath or battale ſhall increaſe</p>
               <p>iiii. Thy dreme ſhalbe trewe</p>
               <p>v. He that thou aſketh for, is ſycke de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ade, or taken.</p>
               <p>vi. Striuyng is not prophetable.</p>
               <p>vii. He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is gone ſhal not com agayne</p>
               <p>viii. The tydynges be falſe,</p>
               <p>ix, In land bought you ſhall not proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</p>
               <p>x, Changyng is good.</p>
               <p>xi, the pore ſhalbe lyghtlye tyche,</p>
               <p>xii, Helth ſhalbe in age,</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The end of the boke,</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
